Mss.Ms.Coll.200
American Philosophical Society
- Papers
  - Letter to Mr. Derry, New York, Dec. 22, 1816; Bonaparte, Joseph, 1768-1844
    Point Breeze. A.L.S. 1p in French. Voices friendliest sentiments and will send him a keepsake.
  - Letter to the Dean of Hereford, Hereford, Jan. 3, 1817; Herschel, William, Sir, 1738-1822
    Slough near Colnbrook, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Suggests that an achromatic refracting telescope made by Dollond is sufficient to view the ring and satellites of Saturn as well as the belts and satellites of Jupieter. Also notes the best time to see these astronomical phenomena.
  - Petition to the Select Council of Philadelphia, Jan. 8, 1817; Sully, Thomas, 1783-1872
    praying that the stand for the hackney-coaches be removed from the front of Philosophical Hall; Photo. of A.D.S. 1p. (from original in the Historical Society of Pennsylvania.) Presented by W.J.Bell, Jr.; May 1964.
  - Letter to Baron Krayenhoff, Jan. 29, 1817; 9x7-1/4; Marum, M. van (Martinus), 1750-1837
    Haarlem, Photo.of A.L.S. 3p. In Dutch. (from original in the Natural History Museum, University of Groningen.)
  - Mémoire éxplicative des productions minéralogique des environs de Paris, Feb. 3, 1817; 13-1/2x7-3/4; Vaurin,
    D.S. 4p.,end."from D.B.Warden" In French. When found in 1959, this item was mounted in scrapbook kept by J.Vaughan. For other material in scrapbook, see: T.P.Smith. List of minerals...;June-Nov. 1800 [1801].
  - The committee of superintendence to Caspar Wister, February 21, 1817; 8" x 10"; Philadelphia. Committee of Superintendence for the Relief of the Poor
    Philadelphia, 1 p., address and endorsement. Pr.D.S.: William Tilghman, Roberts Vaux. Circular regarding the causes of poverty in Philadelphia and vicinity.
  - Elias Horne to James Ferguson, March 12, 1817; 7 3/4" x 9 7/8"; Horne, Elias
    Charleston, 4 pp. and address. A.L.S. Relative healthfulness of Charleston and Philadelphia.
  - Mereorological Observations., March, 1817; 4 1/2" x 13"; Meteorological observations, Cambridge, [Mass.], March--, 1817.
    1 p. Pr.Com. "State of the Thermometer, at a tenament of Mr. James Reed, near the Brattle House, Cambridge.. ."
  - Meteorological observations, April, 1817; 2 1/2" x 11 1/8"
    Cambridge, [Mass.], 1 p. Pr.Com. "State of the Thermometer at a tenament of Mr. James Reed, near the Brattle House, Cambridge."
  - Prezzi correnti di mercanzie in portofranco di Genova..., May 3, 1817; 7 1/4" x 9 5/8"; Prezzi correnti di mercanzie...
    2 pp. Pr.D. (In Italian.)
  - Letter to Professor [William] Wallace, May 8, [1817-1818?]; Sommerville, Mary
    London, A.L.S. 3p.and add. Asks for information about weight and wind resistence to a column to used in architecture.
  - Letter to Monsieur le Comte, May 30, 1817; Lamarck, Jean Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet, de, 1744-1829
    A.L.S. 1p. In French. Letter to gratitude for all that le Comte has done for Lamarck.
  - Letter to [Sir Charles Blagden], June 1, 1817; Biot, Jean-Baptiste, 1774-1862
    Leith, A.L.S. 2p. In French.
  - Price current., June 6, 1817; 8" x 10 1/8"; Dowling, James, and Sons
    Imports. Exports. Bordeaux, 4 pp. Pr.D. Manuscript notations.
  - Letter to [Charles Dietrich Eberhard König], June 25, 1817; Buckland, William, 1784-1856
    A.L.S. 1p. Sends bear's head. Wishes to barter it for mastodon bones, or some such.
  - Meteorological observations, June, 1817; 2 3/8" x 11 1/4"
    --,Cambridge, [Mass.], 1 p. Pr.Com. "State of the Thermometer, at a tenament of Mr. James Reed, near the brattle House, Cambridge.. ."
  - Brief View of the British and Foreign Bible Society, July 16, 1817; 7 1/2" x 9 1/4"; British and Foreign Bible Society
    London, 4 pp. Pr.D.
  - C. Tompkins to John Richards and Company, August 4, 1817; 7 1/4" x 12"; Tompkins, C.
    Richmond, 2 pp. A.L.S. Giving prices of timber and boards.
  - Letter to the Chev. Cuvier, Aug. 9, 1817; 9 3/4" x 8"; Correia da Serra, José Francisco, 1750-1823
    Phila., A.L.S. 1p. and add. In French. Bison.
  - Letter to Amos Eaton, Northampton, Mass., Nov. 1, 1817; 7-3/4x6; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    New York, A.L.S. 2p.and add. Concerning a work on botany. Refers to LeConte's collection,and comments on Mitchill, and the Pursh collection.
  - Letter to Charles M. Watson, Montreal, Dec. 24, 1817; 12 3/4" x 8"; Watson, Elkanah, 1758-1842
    Albany, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Fatherly advice; quotes B. Franklin's saying "a cat with gloves on will never catch mice." FILM54-66 FRAME135
  - Account of the territory taken possession of by the Portuguese N.E. of River Plate, 1817; 8 1/4" x 9 13/16"; Poinsett, Joel Roberts, 1779-1851
    by J[oel] R. Poinsett. ----, 5 pp. and endorsement. Com.
  - Letter to M. Rougé, de maire de Longpont, Jan. 9, 1818; 9" x 7"; Cuvier, Frédéric, 1773-1838
    Paris, A.L.S. 3p. and add. In French. Relative to M. Harmand (?) former instructor at Bretigny.
  - Note of the principle articles of American produce imported into Liverpool in 1817..., Jan. 10, 1818
    1p. Pr.D.S. with an estimate of the average value, free of duty.
  - The ways of heaven are dark & intricate, Jan. 23, 1818; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Bensell, George?
    D. 1p. Poem about Caspar Wistar. Presented by Miss Sarah Madeline Hodge, 1949.
  - Letter to Daniel Moore, Jan. 29, 1818; Buchan, David Stewart Erskine, Earl of, 1742-1829
    A.L.S. 1p., end. Believes it would be descending from Davy's station if he prosecuted the author or publisher of certain newspapers because of the way in which they discussed his discovery of the safety lamp.
  - Letter to James Rush, Feb. 13, 1818; 8" x 10"; Vaux, Roberts, 1786-1836
    A.L.S. 1p. and add. Comments on Benjamin Rush's last official act as president of the Pennsylvania society for promoting the abolition of slavery.
  - Receipt to Nicholas Biddle for Lewis and Clark manuscripts, April 8, 1818; American Philosophical Society. Historical & Literary Committee
    Photostat of D.S.: Jo[h]n Vaughan. 1p. and end. (from original in Missouri historical society.) Presented by the Missouri historical society.
  - Letter to [Parker] Cleaveland, Bruswick, Maine, June 19, 1818; Coxe, John Redman, 1773-1864
    Phila. A.L.S. 3p. add. end. Explains why ended editorship of journal (possibly Emporium of Arts and Sciences); mentions Silliman's publication. Commends Cleaveland for recent work in mineralogy, which he feels will promote interest in study of mineralogy. Mentions Berzelius' discovery of a new alkali.
  - Letter to John Ardagh, June 24, 1818; 6-3/4x4-1/4; Banks, Joseph, 1743-1820
    L. 2p. Copy, in pencil. Concerning a Sea-serpent.
  - Letter to [Sir Joseph Banks], June 26, 1818; Booth, F.
    A.Dr. of L.S. On same sheet with letter from Banks to Booth, June 24, 1818. Sea serpent.
  - Address: W. W. Woodward, Phila., July, 1818; Morse
    A.D. 1p., end. Fragment. Located in Library; July 26, 1974.
  - Letter to Isaac Ward, Oct. 13, 1818; 11x8-1/2; McCahan, John, 1780-1857
    Huntington, Facs.of A.L.S. 1p. Recommends Joseph Saxton for position as watchmaker. Presented by Arthur H. Frazier, frb. 1967.
  - Letter to John Murray, Oct. 15, 1818; Smith, James Edward, Sir, 1759-1828
    Norwich. A.L.S. 3p. and add., end. Thanks for dedication in Murry's book. Smith'sBotany lectures at Institute at Liverpool. East Indian seeds.
  - Letter to ----, Nov. 28, 1818; 7 1/4" x 9"; Volney, C.-F. (Constantin-François), 1757-1820
    Paris, A.L.S. 2p. In French. Concerning the translation of "The ruins" into Arabaic.
  - Statement of receipts and expenditures by the master warden of the port of Philadelphia..., December 15, 1818; 7 3/4" x 9 7/8"; Philadelphia. Auditor-general
    1807-1813, [Philadelphia], 3 pp. and endorsement. D.S.: Geo[rge] Bryan, Auditor General.
  - James Josiah to Benjamin R. Morgan, January 18, 1819; 7 7/8" x 10"; Josiah, James
    Philadelphia, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Regarding expenses at Glouster Point.
  - Letter to John Nichols, Jan. 22, 1819; 7 1/4" x 8 3/4"; Smith, James Edward, Sir, 1759-1828
    Norwich, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Asks for advice in the publication of the correspondence of Linnaeus.
  - Letter to Sir James Ross, Feb. 27, 1819; Wollaston, William Hyde, 1766-1828
    A.L.S. 4p. An analysis of mineral samples brought back from Ross' expedition about the "Isabella"(?).
  - Letter to Sir Joseph Banks, London, April 16, 1819; Barrett, B.
    Zealand. A.L.S. 3p. add., end. Thanks for attention to essay on measurement of periphery. Further comments and calculations on same.
  - Facsimilies of the signatures, April 19, 1819; 13-1/4x10; United States. Declaration of independence
    Broadside. 1p. "I CERTIFY that... I have compared all the Signatures with those of the original and have found them EXACT IMITATIONS. John Quincy Adams." Engraved by J.W.Allen: ornaments by A.H. Wray and engraved by E.M.McCabe.
  - Letter to Chandler Robbins, June 11, 1819; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Banks, Joseph, 1743-1820
    A.L.in 3rd.P. 1p. Is too weak to visit, but would like for him to visit.
  - Frederick Christian Schaeffer to Peter S. DuPonceau, July 17, 1819; 7 7/8" x 10"; B D92p; Schaeffer, F. C. (Frederick Christian), 1792-1831
    New York, 3 pp., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Tour of Baron von Salis in Germany and Austria. Incorrect information about America widespread in those countries. FILM403 FRAME154
  - [Papers pertaining to the case of John Holbrook et al vs. James Prince], July-Dec., 1819; Binney, Horace, 1780-1875
    D. 8 items (14 leaves). Various sizes. Contents: Boston court of common pleas to H.Binney and A.Dawson; Dec. 6, 1819; John Holbrook et al vs James Price; Oct. 1819; Depositions of witnesses (taken by H.Binney and A.Dawson), signed: John Steel; B.Cannonge; William Page; Silas E. Weir; Fred[eric]k Brock; Rob[ert] A. Patton; Letter from W.C.Coolidge to William Page; Sept.17,1819; Letter from James S.Colburn to William Page; Sept.7,1819; Letter from William Page to W.C.Coolidge; Sept. 22, 1819; Account of J.S.Colburn with Peter Graham; July 29, 1819; and Account of J.S.Colburn with George Nugent; July 30, 1819.
  - Letter to Parker Cleaveland, Bowdoin college, Aug. 2, 1819; 12-3/4x8; Eaton, Amos, 1776-1842
    Troy, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. Concerning mineralogical specimens found in the U.S.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Oct. 10, 1819; 10x7-3/4; Logan, Deborah Norris, 1761-1839
    Stenton, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. Concerning Logan-Penn correspondence.
  - Joseph Correa de Serra to J(oel) R. Poinset(t), October 20, 1819; 7 3/4" x 8"; Correia da Serra, José Francisco, 1750-1823
    Philadelphia, 1 p. A.L.S. Regarding candidacy of (Thomas) Cooper for professorship of chemistry at South Carolina College. Copy of letter printed in A.P.S. Trans. n.s., v.45, part 2, p.172.
  - Letter to Sir Joseph Banks, Jan. 10, 1820; 8" x 10"; Hosack, David, 1769-1835
    New York, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Sends various writings including an article which gives additional light on the Franklin-Hutchinson letters. FILM54-61 FRAME217
  - Letter to J.P. Todd, Jan. 11, 1820; 10x7-3/4; Mease, James, 1771-1846
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p.and end. Has the medal been delivered to Col. Taylor?
  - Agreement with William Clark pertaining to certain lands, Jan. 20, 1820; Marshall, Humphrey, 1760-1841
    Copy of D. 5p. (transcribed in letter from Marshall to John and Thomas Maitland, Feb. 2,1820) Mentions George Rogers Clark, William Croghan, Levi Hollingsworth and others.
    - Survey of land in the County of Lincoln on the Ohio, January 20, 1820; 1 map, 30.5 x 27.3 cm; Clark, William
      Annotated: "Surveyed for land for Brigadier General Clark 37,000 Acres of Land by virtue of 25 Treasury Warrants." The land was near the Tennessee and Ohio Rivers.
      Realms of Gold, 33 (8).
  - Letter to John and Thomas Maitland, Feb. 2, 1820; 10" x 8"; Marshall, Humphrey, 1760-1841
    Frankfort, ky., Copy of L. 1p. and end. Regarding agreement, Jan. 20,1820, with Gen. William Clark in re certain lands; transcribes agreement - 5p. With this are miscellaneous notes and a survey of land owned by George Rogers Clark, with whom Marshall also had an agreement - 3 pieces. Presented by the Athenaeum of Philadelphia, June 1957.
  - Letter to [J.] Payne Tod[d], Montpelier, Va., March 24, 1820; 10x7-3/4; Mease, James, 1771-1846
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p.and end. Thanks for delivery of medal to Col. Taylor. Concerning medals of the American Revolution and the destruction of the dies.
  - Henry W. DeSaussure to Robert Patterson, April 22, 1820; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; De Saussure, Henry William, 1763-1839
    Columbia, S.C., 4pp. and address. A.L.S. Also unsigned draft reply. Inquires respecting Mr. Nulty as a possible candidate for professorship of mathematics at South Carolina College.
  - Letter to Amos Eaton, April 24, 1820; 9 3/4" x 8"; Cleaveland, Parker, 1780-1858
    Brunswick, Maine, A.L.S. 1p. and add., end. Acknowledges printed sheets of some work. Is preparing a second edition of his work.
  - Letter to Julius Hering, April 30, 1820; 10" x 8"; Blumenbach, Johann Friedrich, 1752-1840
    Gôttingen, A.L.S. 1p. and add. In German.
  - Memoir copied from Gentleman's Magazine, July, 1820; Dollond, Peter
    D. 1p. Includes autograph of Peter Dollond, Aged 88; 1819.
  - Letter to [Claude Louis Berthollet], Dec. 10, 1820; Berzelius, Jons Jakob, Friherre, 1779-1848
    Stockholm, A.L.S. 4p.,end. In French. Refers to Blagden, Blake, Dulong, Ampere, Gay-Lussac, Arago, Lalande; concerning scientific subjects, such as nickle, magnetism and electricity.
  - Letter to [William ?] Vaughan, 1820; 8" x 5"; Webster, Thomas, 1773-1844
    Bedford Street, Monday [ca.]. A.L. in 3d P. 2p. Exchange of publications between the Geological Society and the Society of Philadelphia.
  - Letter to John Parke, [1820]; Davy, Humphry, Sir, 1778-1829
    Rome, A.L.S. 3p.and end. Wishes his chemical apparatus and some books cleared through customs.
  - Account of steam boat, its cost etc., March 5, 1821
    1p. and endorsement. A.D.S: Christopher Bennett. Estimate of price of steam boat and its engine.
  - [Estimate of price of boat ...], March 12, 1821
    1p. A.D.S.: Samuel Bower. Estimate of $6,000 for a 215 ton boat.
  - Letter to W[illia]m Meredith, May 16, 1821; 10x8; Smith, Robert Hobart, 1792-1858
    A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. Concerning lease to Peale Museum.
  - Letter to "Geologists", Aug. 1, 1821; 3-3/4x6-1/4; Symmes, John Cleves, 1780-1829
    Newport, A.L.S. Draft. 1p.and end. Asks the geologists to declare either for or against his theory of the hollow earth.
  - Letter to M. [Marie Henri] Beyle,Paris, Sept. 25, 1821; 7 3/4" x 6 1/4"; Destutt de Tracy, Antoine Louis Claude, comte, 1754-1836
    A.L.S. 3p. and add., end. In French. Speaks of Beyle's L'Amour; mentions M. Compagnoni, the Italian translator. ----Transcription by Dr. Chinard.
  - Letter to [Marie Henri Beyle], Oct. 10, 1821; 9 1/2" x 7 1/2"; Destutt de Tracy, Antoine Louis Claude, comte, 1754-1836
    A.L.S. 3p. and end. in Beyle's hand. In French. Beyle's De L'amour. Sends letter to Defendente Sacchi. ---- Transcription by Dr. Chinard.
  - Letter to John Le Conte, Oct. 26, 1821; 10x7-3/4; Calhoun, John C. (John Caldwell), 1782-1850
    New York, A.L.S. 2p.and end. Authorizes him to explore Georgia at his own expense.
  - Address delivered by John Davis... before the members of the Agricultural Society of Maine, October 31, 1821; 15 1/4" x 19 1/2"; Davis, John, 1761-1847
    at their annual meeting, Hallowell, 1 p., marginal notes and endorsements. Pr.D.
  - Letter to William Meredith, Dec. 13, 1821; 8x6-1/2; Delaplaine, Joseph, 1777-1824
    A.L.S. 2p.and add. Concerning C.W.Peale and the moving of the Museum.
  - Attempt of a Monography of the American Species of the Linnean Genus Viola, 1821; Schweinitz, Lewis David von, 1780-1834
    Salem, North Carolina; A.D.S. 3p.
  - Letter to [Joseph Goodall], Eton, March 1, 1822; 9x7; Swainson, William, 1789-1855
    A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. Concerning British conchology.
  - Letter to Samuel Parkes, London, April 4, 1822; 9-1/2x7-3/4; Seybert, Adam, 1773-1825
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 3p.and add. Delivered books to Ord for the academy of natural sciences, as requested. State of his health and business in Philadelphia Parkes is member of the APS. Concerning minerals and their study.
  - Letter to M. Carey, Phila., June 4, [1822]; 12-3/4x7-3/4; Miller, Hosea C.
    Xerox of A.L.S.on broadside: proposals for republication of Willich's Lectures... 1p. (from original in Lea & Febiger Collection, Historical Society of Penna.) Wishes to reprint Willich, and would like to sell some copies. Has asked Jefferson if he might dedicate it to the A.P.S.
  - Will, Oct. 17, 1822; 10" x 8", 9" x 7 1/4"; Ingersoll, Jared, 1749-1822
    D. 1p. and end. ca. Att: Dec. 30, 1822. ---- Certification of above document, by J.R. Ingersoll; Dec. 30, 1822. A.D.S. 1p. ---- Inventory. D.S: Elizabeth Ingersoll;, executrix. 1p. 10" x 8" Deposited by the Register of Wills Office, Phila., Dec. 10, 1954 - restricted cf. terms of use, Legal folder. Film 895.3 Frame FILM 895.3 FRAME
  - Arabic manuscript, 1822; 16-3/4x11; Bowdon, Temple
    ca. D. 1p.and end.: "Given me at Paris 1822 by Sir Sidney Smith."
  - Letter to Jesse Buel, Albany, Feb. 1, 1823; 12-1/2x7-3/4; Eaton, Amos, 1776-1842
    Troy, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. Cites his qualifications for post as acting professor of natural history and agriculture.
  - Letter to John Wilson Croker, March 25, 1823; Lardner, Dionysius, 1793-1859
    Dublin, A.L.S. 1p. Asks Croker to "procure the insertion of a review in the Quarterly [Review]" of Lardner's recent mathematical work. Mentions the Edinburgh Review and B. Lloyd.
  - R[obert] H. Rose to R. M. Patterson, May 19, 1823; 8" x 9 3/4"; Rose, Robert H. (Robert Hutchinson), 1776-1842
    Silver Lake, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Experiments upon temperature of water in Silver Lake.
  - Inventoryof the estate of William Temple Franklin, June 14, 1832
    Typed D. 11 leaves. Notarized copy. In French. Presented by James Nolan; April 18, 1966.
  - Letter to General de Division Magny, July 21, 1823; Boyer, Jean Pierre, 1776-1850
    A.L.S. 3p. In French. Enclosed originally in: Gideon H. Hollister to Hamilton Fish; April 5, 1869. Presented by the Estate of Warwick Potter; 4/26/73.
  - Letter to Charles M. Watson, New York, Sept. 20, 1823; 9-3/4x7-3/4; Larned, Lucy Watson
    Pittsfield, A.L. 3p.and add.,end. Mutilated. Wishes his approval of her marriage to B.F.Larned.
  - Letter to the Reviewer of the Phrenological Transactions in the Edinburgh Literary Gazette, Oct. 20, 1823; Combe, George, 1788-1858
    Edinburgh. A.L.S. 4p., ad. Concerning phrenologists and phrenology.
  - Letter to the Editor of the Edinburgh Literary Gazette, Nov. 3, 1823; Combe, George, 1788-1858
    A. L. in 3rd P. 2p. and add. Will not enter into controversy over phrenology in the Gazette.
  - Letter to J[oel] R[oberts] Poinsett, Nov. 10, 1823; 9-3/4x7-3/4; Elliott, Stephen, 1771-1830
    A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. Is glad his health is improved. Concerning the exhibition and the County de Survilliers noted picture. Concerning a museum of natural history.
  - Letter to [James de Carle Sowerby?], Nov. 17, 1823; 9-1/4x4-1/4; Smith, James Edward, Sir, 1759-1828
    Norwich, A.L.S. 2p. Returns prints and comments on them. Keeps some for further study. Remarks on botany.
  - Letter to ----, Nov. 19, 1823; 10x7-3/4; Vanuxem, Lardner, 1792-1848
    Columbia, S.C., A.L.S. 2p. Lists minerals for him to use in a forthcoming publication.
  - Letter to Edward Wedlake Brayley, London, Dec. 15, 1823; Kirby, William, 1759-1850
    Coddenham. A.L.S. 2p. add. Discusses supposed aerolithe found in Coddenham; has interviewed townspeople and "unhealthy youth" who discovered it. Similar spherical stone in Bonn Museum. Enclosed: signed autograph religious verse.
  - Letter to Richard Phillips, Dec. 19, 1823; Tredgold, Thomas, 1788-1829
    Lisson Grove. A.L.S. 2p. add. Asks for notice of his new edition of Esay on Iron to be inserted in Annals (of Philosophy). Makes suggestion for corrections in previously published calculations regarding the expansion of air. Mentions Brande, Dr. Henry.
  - Letter to Bryan Donkin, London, December 31, 1823; Scott, William
    Edinburgh, L.S. 2p., add. Discusses phrenology and the early success of the Phrenological Society of Edinburgh. Speaks of the Society's need of skulls of different nations in order to undertake comparative studies. Asks Donkin's aid in this endeavor. Mentions Combe.
    See Oversize.
  - Palabras de la lengua Darien ó Cunacuna,..., 1823; 6" x 8 5/16"; Palabras
    Bogota, ----, 8 pp. Com. Spanish-Darien Indian vocabulary.
  - Family record, 1823-1966; Hall, James
    D. 4p.,with t.p.of Bible. Presented by Mrs. Lyle L. Jenne; 1970.
  - Letter to ----, Jan. 30, 1824; 10x8-1/4; Humboldt, Wilhelm, Freiherr von, 1767-1835
    Berlin, A.L.S. 3p. In German.
  - Letter to Prof. [Parker ?] Cleaveland, Feb. 16, 1824; 8" x 9 3/4"; Vaughan, Benjamin, 1751-1835
    Hallowell, A.L.S. 4p., add. Astronomical negotiations. Is applying to his brother, John, for aid in finding suitable person to act as French and Spanish master [at Bowdoin ?].
  - Letter to Elkanah Watson, Feb. 18, 1824; 10x7-3/4; Troup, Robert, 1757-1832
    A.L.S. 3p.and end. Concerning a meeting of the board of regents and his ill health. His Revolutionary War service.
  - Instructions. Steam engine without a boiler, March 10, 1824; 8" x 10"; Hawkins, Joseph
    Philadelphia, 2 pp. and endorsement. Pr.D. Includes a certificate signed by James J. Rush and twenty-six others.
  - Letter to Wm. Whitesides, June 14, 1824; 7 3/4" x 12 1/4"; Watson, John F. (John Fanning), 1779-1860
    A.L.S. 1p. and add., end. Relative to a property in Germantown.
  - Letter to Henry Thomas de la Beche, June, 1824; Weaver, Thomas, 1773-1855
    Tatworth. A.L.S. 2p. Sends collections of fossil specimens, some containing shells, care of J.S. Miller of Bristol Institution.
  - Letter to C. Birnie, Tarreytown, Md., Aug. 28, 1824; 10x8; Carey, Mathew, 1760-1839
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. Concerning the tariff. Sends copy of his address to the Philadelphia society for promoting agriculture.
  - Letter to Dr. [Nathaniel] Chapman, Philadelphia, Aug., 1824; 9-1/2x8; Froriep, Ludwig Friedrich von, 1779-1847
    Weimar,Saxony, A.L.S. 1p. Presented Notizen aus dem Gebiete der Natur-und Heilkunde...and wishes to exchange it for Philadelphia Journal of the medical and physical sciences. For volume, see: 505:N84,nos. 7-11.
  - Letter to [Joseph Goodall, Sept. 5, 1824; 9-3/4x8; Sowerby, G. B. (George Brettingham), 1812-1884
    ]. A.L.S. 2p.,end. Concerning shells.
  - Letter to Bois Martin, Sept. 27, 1824; Mumford, Gurdon Saltonstall, 1764-1831
    New York, Photostat of A.L.S. 2p. Lived with Dr. Franklin for two years during the Revolution. Desires information about the Marquis De la Fayette. Presented by Gilbert Chinard, June1947; from original in Dubois Martin papers in Maryland historical society. FILM54-65 FRAME 122
  - Letter to Marcel de Serres, Montpellier, 30 October, 1824; Des Moulin, Charles.
    Bordeaux, ALS 2p.add. In French. About Pecten maximum. Regards to M. Delile and M. Cambenider(?).
  - Letter to M[athew] Carey, Nov. 15, 1824; 8x7; Ingham, Samuel D. (Samuel Delucenna), 1779-1860
    New Hope, Penna., A.L.S. 1p. Agrees to become a member for a society for the promotion of internal improvement.
  - Letter to C. Birnie, Tarreytown, Md., Dec. 14, 1824; 10x7-3/4; Carey, Mathew, 1760-1839
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. Concerning the need for a higher tariff
  - Letter to General Lafayette, [1824]; Philadelphia Bar Association.